Guide to the Flora Hale Foster family papers 1977.310
Brooklyn Historical Society
Flora Hale Foster family papers
1888-1917
Brooklyn Historical Society
Foster, Virginia
McKelway, St. Clair
Foster, Florida Hale
1977.310
0.25 Linear Feet in one box.
Documents, correspondence, and ephemera compiled by and relating to the family of Flora Hale Foster, including her aunt Virginia Brooks Thompson McKelway, her uncle St. Clair McKelway, and her first cousin twice removed, Lansford Foster Chapman.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick Albright on behalf of the estate of Flora Hale Foster, 1967.
Arrangement
The items are arranged roughly chronologically.
Biographical note
Flora Hale Foster was born in 1878 to Florida (also called Flora) Hale Thompson (b. 1853) and Charles W. Foster (d. 1885), who were married in 1874. After her parents' deaths she and her sister Virginia May Foster (b. 1882) became wards of their mother's sister Virginia Brooks Thompson McKelway and her husband St. Clair McElway.
St. Clair McKelway (1845-1915) was born in Missouri and grew up in New Jersey. He was the editorial writer for the Brooklyn Daily Eagle from 1870 to 1878, and editor of the Albany Argus from 1878 to 1884. He was later editor-in-chief of the Brooklyn Daily Eagle from 1884 to 1915. It was during this time that the newspaper became a local success and won a national reputation, and McKelway and his wife came to know many well-known figures of the day, including Mark Twain. McKelway was also a regent of the University of the State of New York from 1883 to 1915.
Flora Hale Foster's father Charles W. Foster was born to Thomas Lansford Foster (1823-1908) and Henrietta Pratt Foster (1828-1903). Thomas Lansford Foster had been born to Asa Lansford Foster (1798-1868) and Louisa Trott Chapman Foster (1801-1861). Louisa's brother Joseph H. Chapman (1803-1886) was the father of Major Lansford Foster Chapman (1834-1863), who died in the United States Civil War.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Foster, Florida Hale. A few verses. 1904. PN6101 .F676 1904
Brooklyn Daily Eagle photographs (BCMS.0002)
Laura C. Holloway letters (BCMS.0020)
Thomas N. Schroth and Raymond A. Schroth, S.J. Brooklyn Eagle collection (ARC.093)
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of documents, correspondence, and ephemera compiled by and relating to the family of Flora Hale Foster, including her aunt Virginia Brooks Thompson McKelway, her uncle St. Clair McKelway, and her first cousin twice removed, Lansford Foster Chapman.
Items related to Foster's uncle St. Clair McKelway include two copies of a pamphlet on Queen Victoria written by McKelway, tributes and memorials to McKelway from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle and the University of the State of New York, a program for a dinner hosted by the Lotus Club in honor of McKelway, and a copper etching depicting author Mark Twain, given to McKelway by Twain.
Also included are autograph books and correspondence of Foster's aunt, Virginia Brooks Thompson McKelway, and poems written by Foster and her sister, Virginia. The autograph books contain inscriptions from many well-known figures. Additional items include notes and a clipping regarding Foster's home, 25 Monroe Place in Brooklyn Heights, and a program for the dedication of a memorial flag and tablet to Major Lansford Foster Chapman of Pennsylvania, who was killed in the Civil War and was Foster's grandfather's first cousin.
Newspaper editors -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Intellectual life; Etchings (prints); Programs (documents); Pamphlets; Newspaper employees -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn daily eagle; Poems; Printed ephemera; American newspapers -- New York (State) -- Kings County; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Autograph albums; McKelway, St. Clair; Brooklyn Daily Eagle (Firm); Chapman, Lansford Foster; Twain, Mark
- Virginia Brooks Thompson McKelway correspondence, 1888, 1913, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Two letters from St. Clair McKelway and one from Oscar S. Straus.
- Virginia May Foster childhood poems, circa 1890s (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Victoria:…a Tribute to our late beloved Queen by St. Clair McKelway", 1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Verses by Florida Hale Foster", 1904 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Autograph books, 1904-1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes inscriptions from Seth Low, Lyman Abbott, Woodrow Wilson, Andrew Carnegie, Julia Ward Howe, Theodore Roosevelt, Booker T. Washington, Edwin Blashfield (including pencil drawings), and Mark Twain.
- "Dinner to St. Clair McKelway by the Lotus Club", 1906 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 25 Monroe Place ownership notes and clipping, circa 1910, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Board of Regents, State University of New York memorial to St. Clair McKelway, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Brooklyn Daily Eagle trustees memorial to St. Clair McKelway, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Lansford Foster Chapman memorial, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Copper etching of Mark Twain inscribed to St. Clair McKelway, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)